מזל טוב Mazel Tov everybody, today's דף Daf is נט Nuntet 59,
we're in the middle of the expansion of the line at the
end of the משנה, Mishna, the first משנה Mishna in the sixth
פרק, Perek, that when you assess the damage done by שן ורגל,
Shein v'Regel, שמינו על פי שדה אחר, shamino al pi sadeh acher,
you assess it based on another field, which basically means two ideas.
Number one is you focus on the damage to the field, not
to the fruit, and you say how much the field's price went
down as a result of the eating of the fruit in the
field, which is much less than if you were just to focus
on the fruit. Then the question is, how do you assess? Because
if somebody's whole field constitutes this one plot of land where the
animal ate, then obviously the damage is much higher than if a
person has a thousand acres. So the גמרא Gemara says שמינו על
פי שדה אחר, shamino al pi sadeh acher, which רש"י Rashi says
means you assess it based on what that damage would have been
in a field that was like sixty times as big, although there's
this whole number of sixty floating around, although it got confusing because
it is sixty plus this idea of sixty סאה, se'ah, sixty תרקב,
tirkav, how exactly do you do the math?
Well, I just wanted to mention that. It is not clear from
רש"י Rashi that it is
your field; רש"י Rashi makes it actually sound like you go by
some standardized model. תוספות, Tosafot, which I did not mention yesterday,
emphasizes that the משנה Mishna actually says שמין בית סאה באותה שדה,
shamin beis se'ah be-osah sadeh, and that what actually רש"י's Rashi explanation
has lost is the idea that the emphasis, תוספות Tosafot actually says
the חידוש chiddush of the משנה, Mishna, or the point of the
משנה, Mishna, is באותה שדה. be-osah sadeh. You actually say how much
was the שדה הניזק sadeh ha-nizak damaged? How much was this person's
field damaged? But the question then still is,
what do you mean? So the guy has a small field as
opposed to a guy who has a big field, how exactly do
you figure it and assess it? So what תוספות Tosafot says is,
this all gets very complicated but I will just put it out
there, what תוספות Tosafot says is that what you do is the
following: you say look, had a סאה se'ah of let's say the
animal ate wheat, had a סאה se'ah of wheat been eaten in
a sixty סאה se'ah field, how much would that סאה, se'ah, that
acre, have been depreciated, the acre which was eaten from? Or no,
excuse me, how much would the whole field have been depreciated? If
they ate from an acre in a sixty-acre field, how much would
that whole field have been depreciated? So the answer is one thousand
dollars. Okay, good. So now what we are going to do is
we are going to say, whatever that is a high number, we
are going to say that we figure out how much this animal
ate and we
do the proportional math. This animal only ate a half a סאה,
se'ah, so it is five hundred dollars; a quarter סאה, se'ah, three
סאה, se'ah, we do the proportional math. But the חידוש chiddush of
still באותה שדה be-osah sadeh is we do not say if it
had eaten a סאה se'ah in a generic sixty סאה se'ah field,
but had it eaten a סאה se'ah in a sixty סאה se'ah
field of this field, imagine this field. Right, prices depending on prime
location and things.
Right, I understand.
So that תוספות Tosafot primarily adds the emphasis that it is on
this field. Anyway, it is all very complicated. Let's continue on נט
עמוד א Nuntet Amud Alef where the גמרא Gemara says the following.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So we had a debate of רב נחמן Rav Nachman and אביי,
Abaye, whether רבא Rava or אביי, Abaye, רבא, Rava, right? We had
a debate of רב נחמן Rav Nachman and רבא, Rava, where it
was, no, we finished that.
Yeah, אמר ליה רבא. Amlei Rava. So רבא Rava said, so רב
נחמן Rav Nachman basically ruled on a certain case with the case
of an אדם המזיק, adam ha-mazik, a person who destroyed a דקל,
dekel, that the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa said you also do this
computation of sixty times and you look at it in context of
a larger field, and רבא Rava disagreed and רבא Rava said that
is a special הלכה halacha by שן, Shein, it is not a
הלכה halacha of אדם המזיק, adam ha-mazik, and then it ended with
him agreeing to disagree about that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
but in the course quoted another ברייתא braisa which dealt again with
the whole case about an animal eating and how you figure it
out in different opinions of the תנאים. Tannaim. So we pick up
with the following: אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
so it is אביי, Abaye, it is about ten lines from the
top on נט עמוד א. Nuntet Amud Alef. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
said אביי, Abaye, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yosi Ha-Glili and רבי ישמעאל
Rebbi Yishmael אמרו דבר אחד, amru davar echad, said one thing. רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yosi Ha-Glili is what we just quoted in this
ברייתא braisa that we quoted yesterday, which is, where is the רבי
יוסי הגלילי? Rebbi Yosi Ha-Glili? Hold on, now I have to find
it again. At the
bottom of
נט? Nuntet?
Thank you.
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yosi Ha-Glili נידון במשוייר שבה. nidon be-mishuyar she-ba.
So רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yosi Ha-Glili has a new approach and
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbi Yosi Ha-Glili says no, you actually, if it
ate a certain acre of grapes, of unripe grapes or whatever, you
actually assess the value not just saying like the sixty and not
saying how much was the field damaged, but you actually ask how
much you look at when the grapes are brought to market, and
if when the grapes are brought to market they're going for one
hundred dollars a bushel and it ate a bushel of unripe grapes,
you pay one hundred dollars. Well, I don't know if it makes
sense that you go based on the price when they'll eventually come
to market. Right now, they're very unripe. But it's an approach that
focuses on the fruit being destroyed, not on the field. And then
it actually says, how do you assess the value of a bushel
of unripe grapes? Nobody buys a bushel of unripe grapes. Well, you
assess it based on how much it'll eventually sell for, which is
funny because that's not really what it's worth. But that's what he
said. Okay, by the way, just to complicate things more, תוספות Tosafot
says even רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili says you sort of
do that math within the context of the cost to the field,
but I won't go there. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay? So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says you assess it based on
the value of how much that will be worth later. So רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael אמרו דבר
אחד. amru davar echad. They both said one thing. רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yose HaGelili הא דאמרן, ha de-amarun, we just said רבי יוסי
הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGelili. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael דתניא, de-tanya, רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael we taught: מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם. Meitav sadehu u-meitav
karmo yeshaleim. The best of his field and the best of his
vineyard he shall pay.
This is about the פסוק pasuk of שן ורגל. shein ve-regel. מיטב
שדהו של ניזק ומיטב כרמו של ניזק דברי רבי ישמעאל. Meitav sadehu
shel nizak u-meitav karmo shel nizak, divrei Rabbi Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael says it's the best of the fields of the ניזק. nizak.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר לא בא הכתוב אלא לגבות לנזיקין מן
העידית. omer lo ba ha-katuv ela lighvot le-nezikin min ha-idit. No, no,
no, what the פסוק pasuk is saying is is that when the
ניזק nizak comes to collect from the מזיק, mazik, he can collect
from the best field of the מזיק. mazik. Now, it's not like
if he destroyed an acre of a bad field he can collect
an acre of a good field. No, if he destroyed a hundred
dollars, then he can collect that hundred dollars from the best field
of the מזיק. mazik. Okay, וקל וחומר ve-kal va-chomer להקדש le-hekdeish and
it's certainly true by הקדש hekdeish that הקדש hekdeish can collect also
from the best field. So the question is רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
clear what it means. It means the field of the מזיק mazik
and it's the type of property he's entitled to collect from. But
what does רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael mean when he says you assess
the best field of the ניזק? nizak? Does it mean that if
he destroys an acre of the bad of the bad property of
the ניזק, nizak, you have to reimburse him based on an acre
of the good property of the ניזק? nizak? Like that's nothing that
we've ever seen so far. So it was discussed earlier. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara does with it here.
Okay, ולא תימא, ve-lo teima, don't read רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael כרב
אידי בר אבין ke-Rav Idi bar Avin like רב אידי בר אבין.
Rav Idi bar Avin. דאמר רב אידי בר אבין de-amar Rav Idi
bar Avin כגון שאכלה ערוגה בין הערוגות. ke-gon she-achla aruga bein ha-arugot.
Like for example, if it ate one patch amongst other patches. ולא
ידינן אי כחושה הוה אי שמנה הוה. ve-lo yadinan ee kishusha hava
ee shmena hava. So you can't just straight say if it destroyed
a bad acre you'll pay you can treat it as if it
destroyed a good acre. But let's say there's a doubt. It ate
one patch of of tomatoes and you don't know it was right
at the boundary line between the, you know, average tomatoes and the
prize tomatoes. And you don't know if the if the section it
ate was from the average tomatoes or from the prize tomatoes. ולא
ידינן אי כחושה הוה אי שמנה הוה, ve-lo yadinan ee kishusha hava
ee shmena hava, if it was from the bad or the good.
In that case, the תורה's Torah telling you assume it was from
the best. דאמר de-amar קום שלים שמנה במיטב, kum shalim shmena be-meitav,
pay the best you know, pay as if it ate the best.
כהשתא kee hashta from what you see now. דהכי לא אמרינן, de-hachi
lo amrinan, we don't say that. So he says מיטב כרמו meitav
karmo means you give it as if it destroyed the best, but
not when you know it destroyed it destroyed grade C you don't
treat it as if it destroyed grade A. But if there's some
doubt as to what it destroyed, you you tip the ספק safek
in favor of the ניזק. nizak. Okay, that's that's one reading of
רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. No, don't say that. That's not the right
reading of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. דהכי לא אמרינן, de-hachi lo amrinan,
we would not say such a thing. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama המוציא
מחבירו עליו הראיה? hamotzi me-chaveiro alav ha-ra'ayah?
It's very interesting, you know, when the גמרא Gemara sort of is
willing to accept like חידושים chiddushim in the תורה Torah you know
like some type of a חידוש, chiddush, but it would rather not
accept a חידוש chiddush that violates a normal principle. Like every now
and then you have it גזירת הכתוב. gezeirat ha-katuv. Okay, but we'd
rather accept an arbitrary law or some type of a חידוש chiddush
if it didn't also violate a like a general principle of how
we do things. So we would rather not read it that way
because that would violate the general principle of המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה.
hamotzi me-chaveiro alav ha-ra'ayah. Is it possible that here the תורה's Torah
telling you here we are going to find a doubt in favor
of the ניזק? nizak? Yeah, it's possible, but we'd rather not assume
that's what it's what it's saying because that goes against our general
principle. Okay, so that's not the reading of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
So what is the reading of רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? אלא במיטב
דלקמיה. ela be-meitav de-lekamei. The reading of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is
that if it destroyed something that is unripe, you look at it
as how it will be when it will be in the future
its best. Okay, ומאן ניהו u-man ihu what is it כי הך
דסליק. kee hach de-salik. That which is gonna come up. So what
it's telling you is like this like what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yose HaGelili said, that if it destroys unripe grapes, you pay as
how much those grapes will be worth when it comes to market.
Okay, so well, then it says מיטב שדהו. meitav sadehu. What is
the best of the field? I know, it's not what we said
before, but that's what we say now. What's the best of his
field? When it becomes in its best state, when it becomes ready
to be harvested. Now, I don't know, to me, I am more
offended by that violation of a principle than by the tipping the
ספק safek in favor of the ניזק. nizak. Like here you're paying
somebody more than the damage was. Okay, the damage was very unripe
grapes which, you know, I assume even though nobody normally buys it,
you could find some way to assess some market value of. And
you're paying based on a much an inflated value of what it's
going to be worth when it goes to market. And you could
say, well, the problem is we have no way of putting a
dollar value on an acre of unripe grapes. Nobody buys just the
grapes. You either buy the land or you buy the finished grapes.
Nobody buys just the grapes. And therefore, since there's no market... Way
of assigning a dollar value, the תורה Torah tells us use this
as the way to assess a dollar value. But to me, that
still seems more unfair than the ספק safek read of רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. Yes?
But it's not a way to value it, but that you're not
doing justice for the person who got damaged unless you're
like paying their that these
grown, it's like if you, I don't know, damage a Major League
Baseball pitcher's hand. Right. It's like you're not just paying, right, the
insurance isn't just going to pay out what...
Right. I mean, that's a good point. I mean, even if you
could say a market value, let's say somebody was buying this acre
of land, how much would they have bought it with the unripe
grapes and without? So that's a market value. What you're saying is
that's all very nice that that's some way of assigning a market
value, but this farmer, his like he was expecting to put food
on the table based on what this was going to produce and
now he doesn't have a way because you just gave him some
difference in the cost of the land. So I hear that. I
hear that. I guess I'm still wondering that, you know, like you
could also say it's not fair to the מזיק mazik because who
knows if these grapes would have ripened and how about deducting all
of the cost of all of the fertilizing and the work that
would have gone into growing them? And so there's still, but I
hear the point. It's just not clear to me why the גמרא
Gemara is happier with this like not precise sort of payment more
than it was with the other reading, like when there's a level
of doubt.
Is it a דבר שבא לעולם? davar sheba le-olam? Like it already
exists, but they're not like unborn.
Right. But the question is how much are they worth in this
state? Why are you paying them for how much they'd be worth
once they're fully developed?
Right, and like something's going to come and destroy it.
Exactly. And even if nothing destroys the crop, it's going to be,
you know, how about figuring out how much the amount of effort
and labor is going to go into it, you know?
That has to be factored into it.
Well, we'll see about that. So we'll
see a little bit of that coming up. Let's take a look.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר מר. Amar mar. So we're going back to this
ברייתא. braita. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon, במה דברים אמורים שאכלה לולבי גפנים
ויחרי תאנים. Bameh devarim amurim she-achlah lulavei gepanim ve-ikhrei te'einim. Where do
you pay the difference of the cost of the field? When it
ate the like the figs when they hadn't even begun to like
the fruit hadn't even begun to emerge. And similarly the vines before
the grape had begun to emerge. That's when you pay the difference
in the field.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says הא סמדר. ha smadar. So that
suggests that once the grape gets to the סמדר. smadar. סמדר smadar
is the like the flower, like once the fruit
actually emerges even extremely unripe, that's sort of like the סמדר smadar
stage.
Okay, so actually no, I think I described it too much. I
think רש"י Rashi says
לולבי גפנים lulavei gepanim is that the fruit actually had just begun
to emerge, and the סמדר smadar is that they've actually ripened a
little, but they're still very much towards the unripe end of the
spectrum. Okay, so הא סמדר, ha smadar, once they've begun, so you
pay the difference of the field what if the actual when the
fruits have like only just emerged, but once it's סמדר, smadar, once
it's ripened a little, presumably רואים אותה כאילו ענבים עומדות לבצור. ro'ina
oso ke-ilu anavim omdos le-batzer.
Presumably he would say then you pay it as if they're ready
to be as if they would be when they'd be ready to
be ripened. The idea we just said before, you look at it
as when they would be ready to go to market. So he
said you look at the field value when the fruits haven't begun
to ripen. But presumably as soon as it's סמדר, smadar, as soon
as it's just begun to ripen, then you look at the future
value of the fruit. So the גמרא Gemara says, "one minute," אימא
סיפא, eima seifa, look at the end of רבי שמעון בן יהודה's
Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda statement: אכלה פגים או בוסר. Achlah pagim o
boser. If it ate פגים pagim is a phrase by the figs,
בוסר boser is a phrase by the grapes. So then it says
you pay as if they're ready to be harvested. Now פגים pagim
and בוסר boser is a stage that's one stage further than סמדר.
smadar. סמדר smadar is when it just begins to ripen, בוסר boser
is it's unripe but it's much closer to the ripe end of
the spectrum.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says right, exactly. הוא דרואים אותה כאילו
ענבים עומדות לבצור. Hu de-ro'ina oso ke-ilu anavim omdos le-batzer. So that's
when you pay it as if they're ready to be harvested. הא
סמדר, ha smadar, presumably when it is just beginning to ripen, רואים
אותה כמה היא יפה וכמה היתה יפה, ro'ina oso kemah hi yafah
vekhamah hayeta yafah, you look at the difference of the value of
the field. So this is of course the classic problem of the
excluded middle, right? He spoke about two extremes and he didn't speak
about the middle. He says when before the fruits have ripened, then
you pay the difference in the value of the field. Once the
fruits are close to being ripe, then you pay as if it
was ready to be harvested. What about the stage in between those
two? Okay, that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רבינא כרוך ותני, Amar Ravina krukh ve-tani, wrap it all in.
במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when do you pay the difference
in the value of the field? בזמן שאכלה לולבי גפנים ויחרי תאנים,
Bizman she-achlah lulavei gepanim ve-ikhrei te'einim, when the fruit has like just
begun to emerge. אבל אכלה סמדר, Aval achlah smadar, but if it
ate it when it was beginning to ripen, פגים או בוסר, pagim
o boser, or even further when it's ripening, in that case רואים
אותה כאילו ענבים עומדות לבצור. ro'ina oso ke-ilu anavim omdos le-batzer. Then
you view it as if they're already ready to be harvested. So
as soon as it's begun the ripening process... put that in the
second category. That's as if it's ready to be harvested. גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says, okay, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if that's true, אי
הכי רבי שמעון יהודה Rabbi Shimon Yehuda. היינו רבי Rabbi יהושע *ei
hachi Rabbi Shimon Yehuda haynu Rabbi Yehoshua* for that's what רבי Rabbi
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* said. רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* if you look at
the very top it's the first words on נ"ט עמוד א *nun
tes amud aleph*, אכלה סמדר smadar רבי יהושע אומר רואין אותה כאילו
ענבים עומדות ליבצר *achla smadar Rabbi Yehoshua omer ro'in otah ke'ilu anavim
omdot lehibatzer*. So if you're putting סמדר *smadar* in for רבי יהושע
*Rabbi Yehoshua* for the רבי שמעון יהודה Rabbi Shimon Yehuda. *Rabbi Shimon
Yehuda* also in the category of as if it's ready to be
harvested, well that's exactly what רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* that's what exactly
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* said, you're both saying the same thing. So
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, איכא בינייהו כחש גופנא ולא מסיימי *ika
beinayhu kachash gufna velo mesaymi*. And here we introduce this point before
that was mentioned before in a small way. No no no, the
question is do you deduct the degree to which the process of
waiting for it to come to market etc. would have you know
sort of depreciated drawn on the nutrients of the ground and somewhat
you know the cost somewhat depreciated the value of the ground. So
basically it's not exactly do you deduct the expenses. If you look
at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* where's the רש"י *Rashi* כחש
גופנא
*kachash gufna*, it's about I don't know about two fifths from the
bottom. ומנכה מן התשלומים מה שיכחישו הענבים בגפנים אם יעמדו שם עד
הבציר שתמיד יונקים לכלות הגפן *u-menakes min hatashlumim mah she-yachishu ha-anavim ba-gephanim
im ya'amdu sham ad ha-batir she-tamid yokim lachlut ha-gephen*. So do you
deduct how much it would have depreciated had it gone to market
by the you know now these vines are very you know you
know filled with whatever nutrients or whatever. By the time the grapes
are ready to go to market, the grapes draw on the nutrients
of the vines and the vines are worth less. So do you
deduct that you know cost that it's cost going to cost me
to bring them to market what it's going to cost in terms
of the value of the vines? Now again to me like I
don't know like I'm not a farmer, I'm not a vintner or
whatever, but to me it would seem that a bigger thing to
figure out about what the difference is going to be is the
cost of my labor, maybe I don't know, maybe grapes when they're
growing requires very little labor to maintain, I really have no idea.
You just check you know water them occasionally or whatever and the
biggest difference is the value to the vines. But so but this
at least introduces if it's not saying all costs, at least it
introduces if we're going to figure out the future value at least
we have to deduct from that payment you know the fact that
you don't now have to you know exert a certain you're not
you're not the cost that you're going to save as a result
that it didn't reach that stage. Okay, so that's going to be
the position. So now what we have is we have two positions
of the תנאים Tannaim *Tana'im* that once the once the fruit has
even just begun to ripen, you are not going to pay based
on the difference of the value of the land, you're going to
pay based on imagining them as complete fruit. Except the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is saying one of these תנאים Tannaim *Tana'im* is saying okay
but at least you get to deduct what this other guy would
have saved you know if not ex- if not losing as a
result of them having to get to that stage. Like maybe his
expense is completely or whatever the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* specifically focuses on
the impact you know that it would have had to the vine.
Yes.
So isn't
isn't the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* and גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* in גזילה עצים
*Gezeila Etzim* make the point that if the גנב *ganav* keeps the
object he still got to pay what the original value was at
the time of the גזילה *gezeila*? Yeah. So isn't isn't that...
I don't understand...
So you can't compare in other words here the damage done you
have to deduct it's like a depreciation amount that you have to
deduct.
Well it wasn't the damage wasn't done to the grapes, to the
ripe grapes, we're favoring the נזק nezek *nezek* by imagining these as
ripe grapes in order to restore a little amount of justice we
have to say you know but they weren't ripe grapes and to
get them to be ripe grapes besides the passage of time right
it would also have been I would say the labor and would
also have been the cost that it would have come in terms
of the the impact it would have had on the vines and
on the ground and so on. So it's restoring a little bit
of a justice to this way of assessing the value. Yes.
I see problems with both sides' approach. First of all is it
the value that the grapes that the grapes futures contract has or
is it the value...
No that the grape has, that's why that's why the problem with
it and that's why the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* to restore some justice
to that mentions this כחש גופנא *kachash gufna* idea.
And the other side change the value of the land. In the
land of Israel there's no such thing as or at least when
the Temple's around when we're doing יובל *Yovel*, there's no such thing
as permanent land sale and the value is going to depend on
where you are in the יובל *Yovel* cycle.
Yeah that's an interesting question and
it's not mentioned here.
Yeah that's an interesting question which I hadn't thought about. Okay so
let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says כחש גופנא ולא מסיימי *kachash gufna velo mesaymi*.
So one of these will assume since now they look like they're
the same position of סמדר *smadar* and so on we don't so
we'll say that there's a difference between them about whether you deduct
the sort of you know the depreciation of the field or whatever
you know the the weakening of the of the drawing of the
nutrients but it's not clear which one would take that position but
we'll assume one of them does and that's the basis of debate.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says אביי אמר *Abaye amar* מסיימי *mesaymi*.
מסיימי ומסיימי, no, it can be identified who is the one that
takes that position, that you deduct the sort of future costs that
would have come to the object. Where do you get this from?
Okay, מאן תנא דחייש לכיחשא. Man tana de-chaish le-khichasha. Now I'm going
to show you that there is one of these two תנאים Tannaim
we know is concerned about the future, deducting the future costs that
would have occurred to the thing. Okay, who is that? רבי שמעון
יהודה. Rabbi Shimon Yehuda It's רבי שמעון יהודה. Rabbi Shimon Yehuda Okay,
I just got to tell you, prepare yourselves. This is going to
be a challenging גמרא. Gemara דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
Baraisa, רבי שמעון יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון בן מנסיא, Rabbi Shimon
Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya, אונס, ones, a rapist who
pays the קנס knas in the תורה, Torah, but he pays damages
because it's treated in הלכה halakha as an act of assault, injury
to a person, an act of assault. So a rapist אינו משלם
את הצער, eino meshalem et ha-tzaar, but the one thing what he's
not going to pay, he'll pay for the damage, the נזק nezek
to the woman, and which then becomes an interesting question, what is
that? How much the woman would have gone in a slave market
as a virgin versus not a virgin? Okay, but now we would
think, I would think that the big payment would be, of course,
the pain and the suffering and the trauma and all of that.
Says no, doesn't pay צער. tzaar. Why doesn't he pay צער? tzaar?
He pays בושת, boshet,
but he doesn't pay צער. tzaar. In the difference of the קנס
knas of the תורה, Torah, there's the standard payments for an act
of חבלה. chabala. And within those standard payments of an act of
assault, he does not pay the צער. tzaar. Exactly. Exactly. מפני, Mipnei,
now why not? שסופה להצטער תחת בעלה. she-sofa le-hitztayer tachat ba-ala.
Well, because what's the צער? tzaar? The צער tzaar is that it's
there's some pain that comes when a woman loses her virginity. Well,
that's going to happen anyway when she was going to have sex
with her husband, so there's no real additional pain here. Like I
don't even believe how anybody can say such a thing. But okay,
like I mean I really don't know what I really can't understand
what you could imagine to say that.
אמרו לו, Amru lo, so the rabbis said back, אינו דומה נבעלת
ברצון לנבעלת באונס. eino domeh nivalet be-ratzon le-nivalet be-ones. Excuse me, the
צער tzaar here is not just the צער tzaar of losing virginity,
there is a big difference with somebody who's willfully participating in an
act of sex and somebody who is being raped. Okay, so all
right, obviously that's the right answer. I have no idea how he
could say something else. But
the reason the גמרא Gemara is bringing this deeply disturbing issue up
is because he's saying, look, רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben
Menasya says that you don't pay the payments that are being made
here to the injury done to the woman, have to deduct from
those payments any type of similar types of costs that would have
occurred in the future. Why should I be paying for some type
of a cost that you're going to incur in the future? Okay,
so they do argue whether you also whether you consider
the basic profound injury that's occurred through the act of rape. But
focusing on the loss of virginity, why should I pay for the
צער tzaar of the loss of virginity if that's a צער דשיחשא
גופא?
tzaar de-shichasha gufa?
Right, so why should I pay? If I'm going to pay for
the grapes, fine, I'll pay for the grapes, but why should I
be paying for a loss that was going to come as a
result of that? So we're going to deduct that from my final
payment. All right, that is the comparison in the גמרא. I think
it's better to just move on. It's what?
Something like יזקי עצמו yizkei atzmo versus יזקי...
I know, but the גמרא is saying is not that you could
have necessarily inferred it from here, but that if we're saying one
of these תנאים Tannaim hold it, and here we see that it's
something that רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya factors in
in a different case, presumably he's the תנא Tanna that holds it
here. Okay, let's move on.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, הני תנאי ורבי שמעון יהודה אמרו דבר אחד.
hanei Tannai ve-Rabbi Shimon Yehuda amru davar echad. Okay, the following תנאים
Tannaim and רבי שמעון יהודה Rabbi Shimon Yehuda, said one thing. So
רבי שמעון יהודה הא דאמרן, Rabbi Shimon Yehuda ha de-amran, so רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon. יהודה we just said, this was his case of
the סמדר and you see it as its whatever, and but also
the way we specifically have focused in now that when there's going
to be a payment, it's going to deduct from it future the
costs that the other side would have had to
endure in the future. If you that should be deducted from what
you're paying him.
So that we saw in רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon יהודה, excuse me.
הני תנאי ומאי היא, hanei Tannai u-mai hi, the following תנאים what?
דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, רבי יוסי אומר נכי
חיה בן עזאי אומר נכי מזונות. Rabbi Yose omer nechi chaya Ben
Azzai omer nechi mezonot. Deduct the cost to the midwife, בן עזאי
Ben Azzai says deduct the cost of the food. What does this
mean? This is another case of paying for something that has not
yet ripened. All of these very challenging comparisons about the case of
the
smiting a woman and causing a miscarriage that you pay for דמי
ולדות, dmei vladot, right, you pay for the cost of the child.
So the question is how do you figure the cost to the
child? Like what a one-day-old baby would have gone on the slave
market for, what the difference in the cost of the woman with
a pregnant woman
who has in the future a pregnant woman slave in the future
will give birth to a baby slave as opposed to a woman
who's not pregnant? So there's a difference there. Like if it's the
current cost of the slave market between a pregnant woman who's a
slave and a non-pregnant woman. one then presumably that's an accurate assessment.
But it sounds like what we're looking here is that these תנאים
think that you actually pay based on how much would a baby
have been going for on the slave market, okay, or how much
if I, you know, sort of abstractly imagined an unborn baby, okay,
and how much would that have gone on the slave market? So
it says, wait one minute, what you're not deducting is the cost
of bringing such a baby to market. Anyway, is, I mean, I'm
saying it in harsh terms because that's the way it's supposed to,
is, you know, it's not a find, but you have to deduct
the costs of that. The cost is how much extra food is
the woman going to have to eat during the period of her
pregnancy? How much are we going to have to pay for the
hospital bills? So I shouldn't have to pay for the full cost
of the baby, you gotta deduct the costs that went into, you
know, to making it, you know, that come in the process. So
one says you deduct the costs of the midwife or the hospital
bills, and one says you deduct the costs of the מזונות, mezonot,
of the extra food that the woman eats. So the גמרא says,
מאן דאמר מקיחיה, man d'amar mikichayah, the one who says you deduct
the cost of the midwife, כל שכן מכי מזונות, kol sheken michei
mezonot, certainly you would deduct the cost of the food. מאן דאמר
מכי מזונות, man d'amar michei mezonot, but the one that says you
deduct the cost of the food, אבל מקיחיה לא, aval mikichayah lo,
you're not entitled to deduct the cost of the midwife. Why? דאמר
ליה, d'amar lei, because the husband of the woman who was injured
could say, איתתא דידי פקיחא היא, itteta didi pekicha hi, my wife
is very smart, she's very talented, ולא מיבעיא חיה, v'la mibaya chayah,
she can give birth without a midwife, okay, like
exactly, כי חיותנה, kei chayotana, it's an interesting play on the חיות.
chayot. Anyway, okay, so therefore you can, I can say, look, that
would not necessarily have been one of my costs. So things that
definitely would have been my costs you're entitled to deduct, but that
would not necessarily have been one of my costs. Okay, now we're
going to move on, wrap up this discussion. רב פפא רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע עבד עובדא כוותיה דרב נחמן בשישים. Rav Pappa Rav
Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua avad uvda k'vatei d'Rav Nachman b'shishim. רב פפא
Rav Pappa and רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna breih d'Rav
Yehoshua פוסקין paskin like רב נחמן Rav Nachman that even when it
was an אדם המזיק adam hamazik who is damaging a, you know,
a palm tree, you assessed it not based on just the value
of the tree, but on the value of the field and you
used this שישים shishim type of a method. לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina,
another version of this is רב פפא רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
שמו דיקלא אגב קטינא דארעא. Rav Pappa Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua
shamu dikla agav katina d'ara. They assessed the value of a palm
tree, which again presumably was destroyed by a person, based on like
a patch of land. So maybe it's not a שישים shishim model,
which makes sense, why should we adopt the שישים shishim model, but
it's still viewing it in the context of the devaluing of the
land and not just focusing on the palm tree by itself, which
is a good question. How would you assess, right, when somebody went
ahead and did it? Would you assess in terms of the land
or in terms of the object? והלכתא, v'hilchata, and the הלכה halacha
is כוותיה דרב פפא רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, k'vatei d'Rav Pappa
Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua, you know what I mean.
קטינא katina is like a little piece of land, I don't know
how they translate קטינא katina over there.
A patch, there you go, a parcel. Okay, והלכתא כוותיה, v'hilchata k'vatei,
as in קטן? katan? Yeah exactly, exactly. והלכתא כוותיה דרב פפא רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע בדיקלא דארמיא, v'hilchata k'vatei d'Rav Pappa Rav Huna
breih d'Rav Yehoshua b'dikla d'Armia, so we rule like them that you
assess the depreciation of the land when you're dealing with an Aramean
palm tree, אבל והלכתא כוותיה דריש גלותא בדיקלא דפרסא. aval v'hilchata k'vatei
d'Reish Galuta b'dikla d'Parsa. But if you're dealing with a Persian palm
tree, then you look at it just in terms of the palm
tree. Why? Because רש"י says that's like a really חשיב chashiv a
tree by itself and you don't, when somebody looks at that, they
don't look at it as like, oh it's a piece of land
with these trees in it, it's like, oh my god you've got
this huge towering oak, and whatever, you know, you focus on that
as the object. So do you assess, by the way, you might
remember before they complained to the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta that he
was דן דינא דפרסא. dan dina d'Parsa. And here we see that
it was a דיקלא דפרסא. dikla d'Parsa. So anyway, but here's a
real good question, like maybe there isn't a rule. Somebody goes ahead
and destroys growing things on a plot of land, do you look
at it as the land was damaged and assess the difference in
the land, or do you focus specifically on the stuff that was
growing? And it might depend on how much independence that growing thing
has, you know, from the land itself, just in the way people
perceive it, I mean in terms of its cost, in terms of
its significance, and so on. Do people perceive this as a part
of the land or do they look at it sort of as
its own type of a thing? Okay, so now the גמרא has
a great little story with ריש גלותא, Reish Galuta, fast, to tie
into the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta theme, but also tie into this
theme of assessing future value. Okay,
אליעזר זעירא Eliezer Zeira ties in also to עניינא דיומא. inyana d'yoma.
אליעזר זעירא, Eliezer Zeira, Eliezer the younger or the smaller one, הוה
סיים מסאני אוכמי, hava sayem masanei uchmei, he was wearing black shoes.
Yeah exactly, that's a good point, I didn't pick up that קטינא
דארעא, katina d'ara, but it's זעירא, Zeira, but anyway. הוה סיים מסאני
אוכמי, hava sayem masanei uchmei, he was wearing black shoes, which apparently
was not the practice. תוספות Tosafot is very bothered, he has other
גמרות Gemorot that sound like black shoes was the practice, so תוספות
Tosafot says, well maybe it was also wearing black shoelaces with his
black shoes. Okay, so anyway, whatever it was, we'll read the גמרא,
he was wearing black shoes, וקאי בשוקא דנהרדעא, v'ka'ei b'shuka d'Nehardea, and
he was there in the marketplace of
נהרדעא. Nehardea. אשכחוה דבי ריש גלותא, ashkechuha d'bei Reish Galuta, members of
the house of the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta found him, and, you
know, bumped into him, saw him. אמרו ליה מאי שנא הני מסאני
amru lei mai shana hanei masani why are you wearing shoes that
are so strange and unusual, why are you wearing these black shoes?
So I don't know, so anyway, but clearly it was some, we'll
see, it had some whatever symbolic significance. מנהג אבל minhag avel well
right, well that's what we're going to see in a minute, right.
I don't want to sort of ruin the surprise, but maybe that's
also what shocked them. You know, here you are, if you're an
אבל avel if you're no, but if you're an אבל avel then
you should be at home. Here you are, you're in the שוק
shuk why are you wearing these things that symbolize mourning? Okay, so
fine. So that's what they were asking him. אמר להו amar lehu
he said to them דקא מאבילנא לירושלים de-ka-m'aveilna Yerushalayim because I'm in
constant אבילות aveilus for the loss of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It's true I'm
not an אבל avel but I'm constantly mourning over the loss of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אמרו ליה את חשיבת לאתאבולי על ירושלים? amru lei at
chashivta l'is-avulei al Yerushalayim? So you, you're so חשוב chashuv what, you're
such a צדיק tzadik every day you're worrying about the אבילות aveilus
of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Like give me a break, like they basically thought
it was יוהרא. yuhara. Okay, so סברי יוהרא הוא. savre yuhara havei.
This person is taking on religious airs. He wants to go around
and sort of present himself like a big חסיד chasid who's always
in אבילות aveilus over ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So they felt that was an
inappropriate way to be acting, who are you to go ahead and
present yourself as such a צדיק tzadik and a חסיד? chasid? So
right, אסיוהו וחבשוהו asyuhu v'chavshuhu so they threw him into jail.
You gotta love the social control that's at play, right? Like you're
not... I don't understand why this was an issue of דבי ריש
גלותא d'vei Reish Galusa to have the social control over people who
thought they were who were trying to present themselves as big צדיקים.
tzadikim. I don't know, maybe because it's also seen as a little
bit of a critique of the current sort of government, the current
status you're living in. ריש גלותא Reish Galusa was the head of
the of the lay head of the you know of the Jewish
sort of political sort of government you know within בבל. Bavel. So
here you are, you're worrying about ירושלים, Yerushalayim, if you're a real
חסיד chasid and a צדיק tzadik fine, that's appropriate. But otherwise maybe
you see it as a personal I don't know critique of somehow
of the current government that you're living under. It's not clear to
me. But whatever, they weren't happy with it. They thought it was
he shouldn't be doing it, they threw him into jail.
Okay, I'm curious about like leather shoes? I don't know. I don't
know.
I mean, I thought אבלים aveilim can't wear leather. I don't know.
I don't know. I mean, it's true, אבלים aveilim wouldn't be wearing
shoes. It's a very good point. Why say מנהג אבל? minhag avel?
Well right, that's what we're...
because he's outside. Well maybe if you're outside, yeah. So okay.
Yeah, I mean if you have to go outside you can.
Right, right. But then why didn't they just assume he was an
אבל? avel? Maybe they knew he wasn't an אבל. avel. I don't
know, a very strange story. Anyway, now we get to the fun
part.
So אמר להו so amar lehu he said to them גברא רבא
אנא gavra rabba ana you're no no no you're not understanding I
really am an
important rabbi, I'm not acting inappropriate to my status, you know I
am I do these righteous type you know these sort of פרום
frum type of things. This is who I am. So אמרו ליה
מנא ידינן? so amru lei mina yad'inan? How do we know you're
such a big rabbi? אמר להו amar lehu he said look I'll
give you like I have this little clergy card I put in
my pocket. No, anyway אמר להו amar lehu he said no oh
here I'll prove it to you. או אתון באו מינאי מלתא o
atun ba'u minai milsa either you ask me a question a like
הלכה halacha question או אנא איבעי מנכו מלתא o ana ib'ei minkhu
milsa or I'll ask you a הלכה halacha question. I'll show you
that I you know I have the goods. Okay now the funny
thing is the people in the house of ריש גלותא Reish Galusa
would be able to assess this person's like תורה Torah knowledge. Anyway
fine. Okay אמרו ליה amru lei so they said to him בעי
את ba'i at you ask us a question, which is also shocking,
right? Because that means that they think that they could answer a
question you know, so
maybe because he was the house of ריש גלותא Reish Galusa that
he knew he was going to be able to best them.
No, but the question is that might no but the question is
why did they say you ask us? Like if somebody said to
me like if some nuclear physicist said to me look either you
ask me a question about nuclear physics or I'll ask you one,
I'd say let me ask you one.
Yeah,
yes, I have this good friend of mine made עליה aliyah years
ago, אלישמח. Elishmach. And he was working living on קיבוץ לביא Kibbutz
Lavi and he ran the hotel lobby and he was cleaning at
the bar and a הדסה Hadassah group of women came, right. And
they said to the the tour guide like you know teach us
some תורה. Torah. So the the tour guide couldn't say anything so
he turned to the guy he said you know in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael even the bartender can give a דבר תורה.
devar Torah. Right, right, even the bartender. So
impressed! Exactly,
exactly. Okay, fine. But I still don't understand why they said he
should ask them. אמרו ליה amru lei they said to him בעי
את ba'i at you ask us. אמר להו amar lehu he said
to them האי מאן דקץ כופרא hai man d'katatz kufra if somebody
cuts down כופרא kufra which is a which is an unripe what
do you call it an unripe date. So מאי משלם? mai m'shalem?
What does he pay? אמרו ליה amru lei they said to him
משלם דמי כופרא m'shalem dmei kufra you pay the value of an
unripe date. So which as רש"י says which is like nobody would
pay anything for it as an unripe date. Okay, so he says
back to it הוה תמרי ha-va t-mari but it's going to be
a ripe date. So then the guy's the owner's losing out. Like
now it's worth nothing, but he's losing out his ability you know
eventually his... it'll be a ripe date and that and he's losing
that out. So אמרי ליה, amrei lei, they said to him fine,
משלם דמי תמרי, mishalem d'mei tamrei, fine pay for a ripe date.
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to them, והא לאו תמרי
שקיל מיניה, ve'ha lav tamrei shakil minei, but it's not a ripe
date now. So אמרו להו, amru lehu, so
he said to them, I'm sorry, אמרי ליה, amrei lei, they said
to him, אימא לן את, eima lan at, fine, you tell us
what the answer is. So אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to
them, בשישים, bishishim, you look at it, you do this שישים shishim
computation. Now, again, I don't exactly get how that answer is whether
it's ripe or not ripe. I mean, if you figure an unripe
grape based on the cost of the larger field, then it's really
worth nothing, you know. So it's not exactly clear to me how
the בשישים bishishim answer, right, the בשישים bishishim answer works better when
you were talking about, like we're talking about one grape here, like
how does the שישים shishim address the ripe versus the unripe thing?
So I really don't even understand the answer. But okay, אמרי ליה,
amrei lei, מאן אמר כוותך, man amar kevassach, who says like you?
Prove to us that that's the right answer. Fine, that's an answer,
but who says that's the right answer? So אמר להו, amar lehu,
he said to them, השמועה חי ובית דינו קיים, hashmua chai uveit
dino kayam, kind of like the חי וקיים. chai vekayam. שמואל Shmuel
is alive and his בית דין beit din is around, go ask
him. שדו קמיה דשמואל, shadu kamei d'Shmuel, they sent to שמואל. Shmuel.
אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, שפיר קאמר לכון, shappir
ka'amar lachon, he said good. בשישים, bishishim, it is שישים. shishim. ושבקוהו,
v'shavku'u, so they, fine, you know, he was in jail the whole
time. Right, he was in jail the whole time. And I don't
know why being a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham necessarily means that you
can be, you're a חסיד chasid to be מתאבל mitabel on ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. I don't understand the whole story, but it was fun. Okay,
if you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says בשישים, bishishim, רש״י
Rashi says three lines from the top, אם קרקע דכל בשישים שהקנה
הקרקע בפירותיה נותן עיניו קצת בשבח של אחר זמן. im karka d'chol
bishishim shehakna hakarka b'peiroteha noten einav katzat b'shvach shel achar zman. Fine,
that's true if you maybe, you know, cut down a whole acre
of unripe date. One unripe date, I don't understand how שישים shishim
is going to make you get any compensation.
Okay, the moral of the story is become a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham and you'll get a get
out of jail free card. Okay, back to the גמרא. Okay, the
גמרא now gets back to the last line of the משנה, Mishna
which is רבי שמעון אומר אכל פירות גמורים, Rabbi Shimon omer achal
peirot gemurim, if he actually ate ripe, totally ripe fruit ready to
be harvested, right to some degree, this is some opinions in the
ברייתא. Beraita. He says, this idea that you assess it based on
the value of the land, that's only if the fruit is not
ripe. If the fruit is not complete, not completely ripe. But once
the fruit is ripe and ready to be harvested, you assess it
as if it's just ate fruit, you don't look at it in
terms of the land, even if it has not yet been harvested.
Okay, so גמרא says, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
אמר רחמנא וביער
בשדה אחר מלמד ששמין על גב שדה. amar Rachmana uvi'er b'sadeh acher
melamed sheshamin al gav sadeh. You look at it in the context
of how much was the field depreciated? הני מילי מידי דצריך לשדה.
hanei milei midi d'tzarich l'sadeh. That's only when the stuff is still
seen as relating to the ground, it needs to draw on the
nutrients of the ground. הני כיון דלא צריכי לשדה, hanei keivan d'lo
tzarichi l'sadeh, since it no longer needs to draw on the nutrients
of the ground, it's ready to be harvested, בעינייהו בעי שלומי, be'einayhu
ba'ei shulumi, you treat it as if it was already cut and
it's just ate straight fruit and you pay, because it's no longer
seen in the context of the field. Fine. אמר רב הונא בר
חייא אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא דן רב כרבי מאיר. amar Rav
Huna bar Chiya amar Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba dan Rav k'Rabbi Meir.
רב Rav in one case actually ruled a real court case like
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir we've dealt with
yet. ופסק הלכה כרבי שמעון. upasak halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. And he פסקן
paskened in theory the הלכה halacha like רבי שמעון. He didn't actually
have a case come in front of him, but he said to
his תלמידים, talmidim, you know, we rule like רבי שמעון in this
issue about פירות גמורים. peirot gemurim. So it's being brought in for
the second part. Let's see what this רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is.
דן רב כרבי מאיר דתניא, dan Rav k'Rabbi Meir d'tanya, it's done
in a ברייתא, Beraita, כתב לראשון ולא חתמה לו לשני וחתמה לו
אבדה כתובתה דברי רבי מאיר. katav l'rishon v'lo chatma lo l'sheni v'chatma
lo avda ktuvata divrei Rabbi Meir. So the הלכה halacha is, if
a man sells a field that his wife has, it's, you know,
her כתובה ketubah lien on, okay, so my wife has her lien
on a particular acre of land and I want to sell this
land here to Michael. Now Michael does not want that lien to
still be on it because he could lose his land. So he
says, fine, I'll buy that land from you if you get your
wife to sign that she's releasing her lien. So I, so I,
so I, so I give him
the שטר מכירה shtar mechira and my wife signs at the bottom
that she's waiving her rights and there he gets it. You know
what the הלכה halacha is? She hasn't waived her rights, because we
assume that she's doing it to make, you know, because to make
me happy or because implicitly she's afraid to say no. You know,
so in that case her signing of it is not a real
waiving of rights. Now, however, if I tried to sell it to
Michael and she refused to sign it, and then I went ahead
and sold it to David and she did sign it, then she
really has waived her rights. Because if she was just doing it
to make me happy, she would have signed on to the first
document. Okay, so that's the הלכה halacha here.
כתב לראשון ולא חתמה לו, katav l'rishon v'lo chatma lo, if the
husband wrote to the first guy and she refused to sign on
it, לשני וחתמה לו, l'sheni v'chatma lo, and then he wrote a
שטר shtar sale to a second guy and she did sign on
that one, אבדה כתובתה, avda ktuvata, she has lost her כתובה. ketubah.
דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, or she's lost her lien on
the land. And רב Rav ruled like that position of רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה אומר יכולה היא שתאמר נחת רוח עשיתי לבעלי.
Rabbi Yehuda omer yechola hi shetomar nachat ruach asiti l'va'ali. No, even
in that case she can say I just did it to make
my husband happy. אתם מה לכם עלי, atem mah lachem alai, you
have no claim against me, I wasn't serious. Okay, so there he
ruled like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ופסק הלכה כרבי שמעון. upasak halacha
k'Rabbi Shimon. What? I assume we go like I don't know I
assume we go like that. Yeah of course yeah totally. Now one
more משנה Mishna which seems almost identical of things we've talked before,
like it seems like we're doubling back on some שן shen issue
wrapping up some שן's shen's שן shen issues and then we will
finally turn to the next משנה Mishna about אש esh and the
rest of the פרק perek will be about אש. esh.
So let's have this
one last משנה Mishna about שן. shen. המגדיש בתוך שדה חברו, Hamagdish
betoch s'deh chaveiro,
somebody like decides to pile up his grain in his friend's field
שלא ברשות shelo birshus and his friend did not give him permission.
ואכלתן בהמתו של בעל השדה Ve-achaltan behemto shel ba'al ha-sadeh
and the owner of the field ate it, פטור, patur, yours is
obvious, which is like quite obvious why he's פטור. patur. You're only
חייב chayav in שדה אחר. sadeh acher. No no no the בהמתו,
behemto, I'm sorry did I not say that? בהמתו של... behemto shel...
Okay so the animal of the owner ate it, so he's פטור
patur which is quite obvious like שן shen you're only חייב chayav
in רשות הניזק. reshus ha-nizak. You're not even חייב chayav in רשות
הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, certainly you're not חייב chayav in your own field.
What would it be if he was hit actually?
Then he'd be חייב, chayav, okay. פטור. Patur. ואם הוזקה בהן, Ve-im
huzka ba-hen, if the animal slipped and was damaged, so then it's
a type of like a בור bor essentially. בעל הגדיש חייב, Ba'al
ha-gadish chayav, then the owner of the of the stack is חייב,
chayav, of the hay stack or whatever the grain stack. ואם הגדיש
ברשות, Ve-im higdish birshus, if he had permission to stack his grain
there, then בעל השדה חייב, ba'al ha-sadeh chayav, then and now this
is also the חידוש chiddush that that's enough to consider it a
type of and then he does pay. The owner of the שדה
sadeh pays if his animal eats it. Now the question is why
does the owner of the שדה sadeh pay if his animal eats
it? I gave you permission to bring it in, my animal ate
it, I could say fine I gave you permission to bring it
in but it's still not שדה הניזק. s'deh ha-nizak. It's still being
eaten in my field, not in your field. Like how's this any
better than רשות הרבים? reshus ha-rabim? You had a right to be
here, you had a right to be in רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabim.
What happens if my animal eats it in רשות הרבים? reshus ha-rabim?
פטור. Patur. So why when my animal eats it and you have
a right to be in my רשות reshus am I חייב? chayav?
This is this whole thing we had before.
Oh okay.
So if you wanted to keep in the שן shen model, which
is what none of you said, but if you wanted to keep
in the שן shen model you could say if I give you
a permission to bring this stuff in it's like I'm temporarily lending
you the land and that little plot of land that it's on,
it's not anybody can use that land, I've given you the rights
to use that land. So that little plot of land that it's
on in my in my yard is actually רשות הניזק. reshus ha-nizak.
That's what you could say. Okay. Alright I'm getting that. So one
way you could frame it is that it's a type of a
רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak keeping within the שן shen model. But what
everybody here is saying is if I tell you sure come into
my come bring it in then then I'm accepting responsibility based on
what happens to it. Which there are there are consequences to that.
Let's say a wild animal came and ate it, would I have
to reimburse you? Right? So that's the question is am I now
חייב chayav because of שן shen or am I now because I've
accepted שמירה? shmira? So we discussed those issues before. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. נימא מתניתין דלא כרבי. Naima masnisin de-la ke-Rabbi.
Let's say our משנה Mishna that says as soon as you give
the guy permission you become liable goes against רבי because you might
remember רבי says you're not liable until you explicitly accept responsibility for
what's going to happen. דאי רבי הא אמר De-i Rabbi ha amar
עד שיקבל עליו בעל הבית לשמור ad she-yekabbel alav ba'al ha-bayis lishmor
that you are not responsible for the animal ate it even if
you let the guy come in unless you say I accept responsibility
to watch the stuff that you're going to bring in. So אמר
רב פפא הכא בנטרי בי דרי עסקינן. Amar Rav Pappa hacha bi-natrei
bei darei askinan. Here we're talking about the watching that goes on
during the threshing like in the threshing floors. בי דרי Bei darei
meaning basically like it's a people are everybody is bringing their grain
into one person who's got a big threshing floor and this is
like whatever presumably they pay him or whatever they do this is
the practice. And therefore it's understood at this that the implicit contract
in this context is that the owner is accepting responsibility. I assume
I hope he's getting paid for his service but he's accepting responsibility
for the stuff that's being brought in. בנטרי בי דרי עסקינן. Bi-natrei
bei darei askinan. Where am I? דכיון דאמר ליה עייל ואגדש De-keivan
de-amar lei ayyel ve-agdash once he tells the guy bring it in
and you can pile up your grain, עייל ואנטר לך הוא ayyel
ve-antar lach hu it's like he's saying it come in and I'll
watch it. So in this a particular context where the acceptance of
שמירה shmira is implicit. Of course if it was only that particular
context why didn't the משנה Mishna. say it? Alright. Now that is
the end. It's basically something we've seen before. We have wrapped up
שן ורגל. shen va-regel. Very bizarre of course you know the order
that these משניות Mishnayos go in. Like why even have these two
משניות Mishnayos at the beginning of המניח Ha-maniach like way back when
we were dealing with שן ורגל? shen va-regel? I don't know. But
now we move on to אש. esh.
And the chapter division sir.
I know. המשלח את הבעירה ביד חרש שוטה וקטן Ha-meshaleach es ha-be'eirah
be-yad cheresh shoteh ve-katan and something that has been quoted a lot
now we're finally seeing it in the משנה. mishnah Somebody who sends
a
torch in the hands of a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh ve-katan.
Now maybe it even means just sends them on a message but
maybe it could even mean sends them to torch somebody's yard. פטור
בדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים Patur be-dinei adam ve-chayav be-dinei shamayim is
exempt from in human court
but
liable in
the court of heaven.
If somebody else's yard, not your yard, right, not your kid?
Yeah, yeah. If שולח sholei'ach actually means you sent them to do
it, right, why isn't that considered, why aren't they considered like a
רוח מצויה, ru'ach metzuyah, meaning why do we say oh you're a
גרמא gerama you're פטור? patur? You had a fire, you introduced a
force into this fire like a רוח מצויה ru'ach metzuyah that was
going to bring it to somebody else's field, right? Why not? And
presumably it's because even though they are not considered בר דעת bar
da'at like legally you know of an age of majority or whatever,
but they still are making their own choices, and therefore somehow that
detaches it from being your act. It makes it their act, and
then you can't collect from them because they're not liable for their
act, and therefore you wind up being this unfair situation, so we
say פטור בדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur bedinei adam vechayav bedinei
shamayim. But it is interesting, and I think in a way it's
a little bit like okay so from the נזק point it's unfair,
but from the aspect of what it's saying about a חרש שוטה
וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, that we don't just look at them as
some like force of nature and that it's an אש eish with
a רוח מצויה, ru'ach metzuyah, we actually say no no no, if
they're taking the fire that's their act now, it's no longer your
act, right? So I think that there's something like important about that.
Okay. Remind us the רוח מצויה ru'ach metzuyah would not be a
case of גרמא? gerama?
רוח מצויה ru'ach metzuyah is the חיוב chiyuv of אש. eish. I
make a fire and a רוח מצויה ru'ach metzuyah spreads it, right?
Or I put a knife up on a roof and a wind
blows it down, that's all a case of an אש. eish. So
I have a fire here and I've put it in the hands
of a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, let that be a
case of אש. eish. No, somehow because they're doing it, even if
they're not considered like of legal responsibility, it's still their act, it's
still their, right, exactly. Okay. שולח ביד פיקח הפיקח חייב. sholei'ach beyad
pikei'ach hapikei'ach chayav. If you sent like let's say for example let's
say it wasn't a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, let's say
I took here's a great example, I took a fire and a
torch and I tied it to the back of my dog and
then I set my dog away. Presumably I would totally be חייב,
chayav, right? That's a רוח מצויה, ru'ach metzuyah, right? The fire's going
to spread, I put it on the back of my dog and
he's going to go and he's going to carry it in other
places. So it's very important that this once it's in the hand
of a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan that becomes their fire
and not my fire. Okay. שולח ביד פיקח הפיקח חייב. sholei'ach beyad
pikei'ach hapikei'ach chayav. And if I sent it through a person who
is an adult and of right mind and of legal responsibility, הפיקח
חייב. hapikei'ach chayav. Not only am I פטור, patur, he's חייב. chayav.
And the fact that I told him to do it does not
get him off the hook like I cannot say I was following
orders, right? It's דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד דברי מי שומעים. divrei harav
vedivrei hatalmid divrei mi shom'im. So even though I sent him, he's
חייב. chayav. Now אחד הביא את האור ואחד הביא את העצים המביא
את העצים חייב. echad heivi et ha'or ve'echad heivi et ha'eitzim hameivi
et ha'eitzim chayav. So I bring a fire and Michael comes and
it's whatever it's a torch but it's whatever it is, Michael comes
and he dumps down all the wood and makes it into a
big fire. המביא את העצים חייב. hameivi et ha'eitzim chayav. So Michael's
חייב. chayav. You're not חייב chayav for anything? Presumably no.
אחד הביא את העצים
ואחד הביא את האור המביא את האור חייב.
echad
heivi
et ha'eitzim ve'echad heivi et ha'or hameivi et ha'or chayav. Or now
let's say the order was reversed. Michael put like a nice little
woodpile and I came and I torched it and I put the
fire to the woodpile. Then המביא את האור חייב. hameivi et ha'or
chayav. I'm חייב chayav obviously, I made the fire. Now the interesting
חידוש chiddush here is is that we don't say in the first
case even though Michael made it a much bigger fire, do we
assume that without Michael's wood it wouldn't have spread at all, right?
Or do we say I don't know, let's say it was a
medium-sized fire and we could actually imagine that it would have spread
to a certain degree, but because of Michael's wood it would have
spread more. Is it like we both dug the well? Like I
think an interesting analogy would be you remember the well that I
dug nine and then somebody dug ten, right? So maybe there's like
an analogy to be made here. Like at what stage do we
say there was a hazard being created, but what Michael did was
so qualitatively different that it completely means that I'm out of the
picture? Okay. Or do we have to say this only when what
I did was no hazard at all? The משנה mishnah. does not
spell out those important details.
Like putting a rock in front of a well, right? אבנו סכינו
ומשאו. ivno sakino umaso.
Right, although I think this is more similar to the well nine
and the well ten, where both creating a fire, I did the
first part, but the second thing was you know made it of
a different degree. Okay. המביא
את האור חייב. hameivi et ha'or chayav. בא אחר וליבה. ba acher
velibah. Now let's say somebody we had a fire with wood and
somebody came and he blew on it and made it a big
one. המלבה חייב. hamelabeh chayav. The blower is חייב. chayav. Which of
course raises the question, are we saying only if it couldn't have
spread without that, right? What if it's always the last, even if
it totally could have spread without that, just the last guy accepts
all the responsibility? Like the critical points are missing from the משנה.
Mishna Okay. ליבתה הרוח כולם פטורים. libata haru'ach kulam pturim. And the
most challenging is this last thing: if the wind blows it they're
all פטור. patur. So does that mean now so that's the whole
case of אש? eish? So תוספות Tosafot says are we talking about
a רוח מצויה? ru'ach metzuyah? If we're talking about a רוח מצויה
ru'ach metzuyah then why are you פטור? patur? So תוספות Tosafot has
two possibilities. One possibility is we are talking about a רוח מצויה.
ru'ach metzuyah. You know why you're פטור patur though? Because before the
wind came along... It’s one thing that you have a fire and
the wind spreads it. Okay, here you did not yet have a
fire. You had something that could become a fire. So the wind
made it—this is actually what the משנה Mishna sounds like—the wind made
it into the hazard, made it into the fire, so it’s the
wind’s fire, it’s not your fire. If it’s your fire and the
wind spread it, then you’re חייב. chayav.
But if it—how did its fire get there then?
No, no, no, it was a tiny little thing that would have
died out by itself, okay? And even though the wind was a
רוח מצויה, ruach metzuya, I didn’t make an אש. aish. I didn’t—an
אש aish is defined as a type of fire that can spread,
and this is not a fire that can spread. This right now,
if there was no wind, would go out. So even though it
could be anticipated that the wind would come and it was a
רוח מצויה, ruach metzuya, nevertheless I’m פטור, patur, it’s not my fire.
Now תוספות, Tosafos, that seems you know unjust, but we’ve had unjust
things before because they don’t fit into a formal category, but based
on anyway other evidence from an earlier discussion תוספות Tosafos rejects that.
And תוספות Tosafos says even if you didn’t make a big fire,
even if you made a fire that would go out, if it
was a רוח מצויה ruach metzuya and it made it into a
big fire, you’re חייב. chayav. That’s still אש. aish. And therefore he
says the case in the משנה Mishna, is that the wind is
a רוח שאינה מצויה. ruach she'eina metzuya. ליבתה רוח וכולם פטורים Libta
ruach vechulam paturin is a type of רוח ruach that could not
have been anticipated, made it a big fire, then we’re exempt, but
if it could have been anticipated, we’re חייב. chayav. Okay, let’s read,
just read to finish the דף. daf. אמר ריש לקיש משמיה דחזקיה,
Amar Reish Lakish mishmei d'Chizkiya, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said in the
name of חזקיה: Chizkiya: לא שנו אלא שמסר לו גחלת וליבה. Lo
shanu ela shemasar lo gacheles veliba.
When is it that when you give it to a חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan you’re exempt? Is if you gave them an
ember and they blew it into a flame, okay, that they really
take ownership over the fire. אבל מסר לו שלהבת חייב. Aval masar
lo shalheves chayav. But if you gave a live flame, you’re חייב
chayav when you give it to a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh
vekatan. מאי טעמא מסרה כח גורם לו. Mai ta'ama? Masrah koach gorem
lo. Because your actions ultimately, you knew they were going to—you gave
them a live flame and they spread it, so it—it would be
sort of like a רוח מצויה, ruach metzuya, what I was just
saying against in the משנה, they would say no, it would be
a רוח מצויה. ruach metzuya. If they made it into a flame,
then it becomes theirs. But if it was already a flame, similar
to what we were just discussing a minute ago, right? Then even
though they’re חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, you’re חייב. chayav. ורבי
יוחנן אמר אפילו מסר לו שלהבת פטור. VeRabbi Yochanan amar afilu masar
lo shalheves patur. Even if you gave them a live flame, you’re
exempt. מאי טעמא צבתא דחרש קא גרים ליה. Mai ta'ama? Tzafta d'cheresh
ka garim leh. It was the holding of the חרש cheresh that
caused it, which means ultimately even though you could have anticipated it
and you could see a חרש cheresh as a type of רוח
מצויה, ruach metzuya, ultimately what he’s saying is the חרש cheresh was
the one who spread it and not you. So if it—even if
it started as a flame, the act gets associated with the חרש.
cheresh. What? Well the גמרא elsewhere ties this in—and you don’t have
to see it that way, right? You could see it—I’m going to
say, you could see it as this question about how do we
view a חרש cheresh as like a רוח מצויה ruach metzuya and
how much do we view like the act of a חרש cheresh
as being significant. But Hillel correctly reminds us that the גמרא earlier
connected this to the debate of אשא משום חציו asha mishum chitzav
and אשא משום ממונו. asha mishum mamono. And the more that אשא
asha is משום ממונו, mishum mamono, the less you need a direct
connection to you, so the more you could say you’re חייב chayav
through a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh vekatan. The more אשא asha
is משום חציו, mishum chitzav, it’s your act, the more intervening another
person in it makes it less your act. So that also is
a part of a question of how you conceptualize the obligation of
אש. aish. Okay, so according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, we’ll just
end with this line, דלא מחייבת אלא שמסר לו גוזא סילתא שרגא.
d'la mechayaves ela shemasar lo guza silta sharga. You’re only חייב chayav
unless you give him like flax and lighter fluid and the flame,
like you know it’s a conflagration ready to burst. In that case
דהוא ודאי מעשה דידיה גרמי, d'hu vadai ma'aseh didei garmi, that’s definitely
your act. And Hillel is correct to again emphasize that because the
phrase of מעשה דידיה ma'aseh didei is evocative of that issue of
אשא, asha, you know, משום חציו. mishum chitzav. That when it’s like
the חרש cheresh is really doing nothing, like it just required a
spark to get it to spread, then it doesn’t become the חרש’s
cheresh act and it really is your act and then you’re חייב.
chayav. So it’s possible this is all just about how you see
when a חרש cheresh sort of takes ownership of the act, which
is an interesting question about what status do the Rabbis give a
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan even though they’re not בני חיובא,
benei chiyuva, or it could be what you see the חיוב chiyuv
of אש aish to be about. And the more that it’s only
about חציו, chitzav, you know then the more you would need a
direct connection to the person himself. Okay, that’s it for today.